Guide to the Manchester Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Albums, 1697/98 Feb 8; Series I
  - G. Stepney to the E of M, recommending Mr. Hicks to his notice. Brussells, 1707 Mar 28 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - The E of M to Lord Godolphin, giving an account of an interview with the Pensionary, expressing a belief that the Duke of Marlborough would "find all things well at his arrival," and touching very briefly on various points in the military and political situation. The Hague, 1707 Mar 29 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - The Electress Sophia of Hanover to the E of M, thanking him for his attachment to her House. (In French. A translation is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 436) Hanover, 1707 Apr 1 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - The Earl of Sunderland to the E of M, mentioning enclosure of a copy of a project concerted with the Duke of Savoy for entering France. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 439) Whitehall, 1707 Apr 4 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - M. de Robethon to the E of M, mentioning enclosure of a letter from the Elector of Hanover. Their Electoral Highnesses held the Earl in high esteem. (In French) Hanover, 1707 Apr 5 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - The Elector George Louis of Hanover to the E of M, expressing regret that the Earl had been unable to pass though Hanover. (In French. A translation is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 437) Hanover, 1707 Apr 5 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - The E of M to the Duke of Marlborough, mentioning enclosure of an important paper given to the Earl by the bearer of the letter. (Draft. Printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 437) Düsseldorf, 1707 Apr 5 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - The Earl of Sunderland to the E of M, directing him to lose no time in pressing upon the Court of Vienna the matters upon which he was instructed. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 441) Whitehall, 1707 Apr 18 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - The E of M to the Duke of Marlborough, expressing hopes that the court of Vienna would at least defer the intended expedition to Naples, though they were "very fond in that matter." Fears were entertained at Vienna respecting the movements of the King of Sweden. It would be hard to satisfy the Duke of Savoy with the proceedings of the Imperial Court. (Draft.) Vienna, 1707 Apr 27 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - [The E of M] to M. de Robethon, requesting him to thank the Elector and Electress of Hanover for their letters. "A great scheme in the affairs of Europe" was now being undertaken, which it was to be hoped that the King of Sweden would not thwart. All eyes were upon the Duke of Marlborough. (Not signed. Endorsed "Not copied"), 1707 Apr 30 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Extract from a letter from Mr. Robinson, giving an account of the reception of the Duke of Marlborough by the King of Sweden at Halle, and of the proceedings of the Duke before his departure for Berlin. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 442) Leipzig, 1707 May 4 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - The Earl of Sunderland to the E of M, renewing instructions to dissuade the Court of Vienna from the expedition to Naples, and to persuade it, if possible, to give reasonable satisfaction to the Duke of Savoy. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 447) Whitehall, 1707 May 6 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Robert Harley to the E of M, to the same effect, but insisting more particularly upon the French success in Spain as an argument to be used. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 447), 1707 May 6/17 (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Queen Anne to the Emperor, urging upon him the importance of making a diversion by invading France, after the French success in Spain. (Copy. In French. A translation is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 448) Kensington, 1707 May 6 (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - The Earl of Sunderland to the E of M, instructing him that the Court of Vienna would never have the Queen's consent to their project upon Naples. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 453) Whitehall, 1707 May 9 (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - [The E of M] to the Duke of Marlborough, informing him that the Austrian troops (about 10,000 in number) were on the march for Naples, but that the Court of Vienna promised the expedition into France should not be prejudiced in consequence. An enclosure relating to the Duke of Savoy is mentioned. Great reliance was placed upon England by the Imperial Court. They would do whatever His Grace thought was for the common good. The Earl would send the patterns for "my Lady Duchess." (Signature wanting. Paper torn), 1707 May 11 (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - Undirected letter from Count Ardizzoni, Minister of State of the Duke of Mantua, complaining that the Duke was kept out of possession of Montferrat and other fiefs dependent on the Holy Roman Empire. (In Latin. Copy. Endorsed "Sent by Broughton unto the Earl of Sunderland at the instance of the Duke of Mantua." A translation, headed "to the Earl of Sunderland," is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 446) Venice, 1707 May 12 (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - The E of M to the Lord Treasurer (Lord Godolphin), expressing doubts whether the Imperial Court would aid the invasion of France, and giving some particulars of the European situation as affecting Italy, Sweden, Poland, Hungary, etc. (Copy. Printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 452), 1707 May 18 (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - Le Sieur J.J. Hamel Bruyninx to the E of M, mentioning an enclosure received from the Prince of Salm, apparently on the subject of the Naples expedition. (In French), 1707 May 18 (Box 10, Folder 28)
  - The E of M to the Duke of Marlborough, mentioning an enclosure which related to the affairs of the Duke of Savoy and another enclosure which was an extract from a letter from the Prince of Salm, and describing the relations of Sweden with the Emperor. (Copy. Reference is made to this letter, though it is not printed, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 453) Vienna, 1707 May 18 (Box 10, Folder 29)
  - The Duke of Marlborough to the E of M, to the effect that he intended to join the army at Halle, and there was a prospect of a battle. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 448) Brussels, 1707 May 17 (Box 10, Folder 30)
  - Count Tarin to the E of M, regretting that he had had no better success than the Earl in his diplomacy at the Court of Vienna, and requesting the Earl to confer with the Marquis de Prié. (In French) Vienna, 1707 May 22 (Box 10, Folder 31)
  - The Duke of Marlborough to the E of M, expressing his desire to give battle to the enemy, in order to repair the misfortune in Spain. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 453) Camp at Lembecq, 1707 May 25 (Box 10, Folder 32)
  - H. Boyle to the E of M, to the effect that the French had 90,000 men in Flanders, and that the Queen was detained in town by the excess of business connected with the Union. As Bonincini could not be "got over" to England, it would be necessary to be content with having his music, especially his new opera. (Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne." ii., 223) London, 1707 May 27 (Box 10, Folder 33)
  - Robert Sutton to the E of M, on the relations of the Port and the Tartars with the Empire and with Muscovy, and on the probable maintenance of peace by Turkey for at least a year. (Printed, Cole's Memoirs, p. 436) Pera of Constantinople, 1707 Jun 6 (Box 10, Folder 34)
  - James Cressett to the E of M, to the effect that the Electress of Hanover considered the Earl to be one of her friends, and would receive a letter from him with pleasure. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 395) Hanover, 1701 Jun 20 (Box 10, Folder 35)
  - The Earl of Sunderland to the E of M, informing him of the Queen's desire that the Duke of Savoy should obtain satisfaction at the Court of Vienna. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 459) Whitehall, 1707 Jun 24 (Box 10, Folder 36)
  - Robert Sutton to the E of M, describing a serious conspiracy to depose the Sultan, and stating that the French had sent nearly 200,000 dollars to the Hungarian malecontents. (Printed, almost in full, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 461) Pera of Constantinople, 1707 Jul 6 (Box 10, Folder 37)
  - The E of M to the Lord Treasurer (Lord Godolphin), giving a description of the character of the Duke of Savoy, and of the political situation as affected by the age and health of the Emperor, his wife, and King Charles, and by the expedition to Naples. (Draft, with many interlineations and alterations.) Venice, 1707 Jul 6 (Box 10, Folder 38)
  - The Earl of Sunderland to the E of M, assuring him of the Queen's continued support of the Duke of Savoy. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 462) Whitehall, 1707 Jul 11 (Box 10, Folder 39)
  - Joseph Addison to the E of M, sending a copy of a short letter from Lisbon on the affairs in the peninsula. Whitehall, 1707 Jul 15/26 (Box 10, Folder 40)
  - J. Vanbrugh to the E of M, giving a description of an enclosed design for restorations at Kimbolton, etc. (Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii. 227) London, 1707 Jul 18 (Box 10, Folder 41)
  - J. Chetwynd to the E of M, announcing that the land forces were within four marches of Toulon, and that Sir Cloudesly Shovell had appeared off the Isle of Hiéres. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 461) Camp at Frejus., 1707 Jul 8/19 (Box 10, Folder 42)
  - Lord Halifax to the E of M, expressing thanks for a Cantata of the Emperor's own composition, as well as other musical works, and an opinion that the Emperor would excel his predecessor in music more than in politics. The Cantata was so good that Bonincini might be suspected to have "had a hand in it." Blackall would not be made Bishop of Exeter, but Dawes would be made Bishop of Chester, and Dr. Trimnel, Bishop of Norwich. (Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii. 231), 1707 Jul 19/30 (Box 10, Folder 43)
  - M. Boury to the E of M, to the effect that there was nothing new to report of the armies of the Netherlands. (In French) The Hague, 1707 Jul 22 (Box 10, Folder 44)
  - The Earl of Sunderland to the E of M, expressing fears that the Emperor would not, after his success in Naples, aid in the expedition against France, but would adhere to the practice of "riding a new acquired country with German garrisons." (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 466) Whitehall, 1707 Jul 25 (Box 10, Folder 45)
  - C. Godolphin to the E of M, mentioning enclosure of a memorial relating to claims of the Godolphin family in the Venetian lawcourts, and giving explanations. (Signed only by C. Godolphin) London, 1707 Jul 25 (Box 10, Folder 46)
  - The same letter, written and signed by C. Godolphin. London, 1707 Jul 25 (Box 10, Folder 47)
  - Lord Raby to the E of M, to the effect that there was uncertainty respecting the designs of the King of Sweden, and that the position of the Imperial army was improved. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 463) Berlin, 1707 Jul 26 (Box 10, Folder 48)
  - Le Sieur J.J. Hamel Bruyninx to the E of M, lamenting the inaction in the Netherlands, and expressing his opinion that the Imperial movements would be too late, and that to attempt to make anything better of a German was as hopeless a task as to wash a black-a- moor white. (In French) Vienna, 1707 Jul 27 (Box 10, Folder 49)
  - Sir Cloudesley Shovell to the E of M, giving some details of the preparations for an attack upon Toulon, but expressing doubts of the result. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 467) Fleet before Hiéres, 1707 Jul 27 (Box 10, Folder 50)
  - A. Stanyan to the E of M, giving a description of the Tribunal for settling the claim of the King of Prussia to Neufchâtel, and expressing his belief "that the weighty arguments of religion and liberty will turn the scale in our favour if we pay as much for justice as any of our competitors." Some details of the forces for the invasion of France are added. Six pages, of which the first four are printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 463) Neufchâtel, 1707 Jul 29 (Box 10, Folder 51)
  - Sir James Montague [Montagu] to the E of M, giving an account of the proceedings in Parliament after the Union, with some family and other gossip. (Endorsed "Baron Mountague") London, 1707 Jul 29 (Box 10, Folder 52)
  - Sir James Montague [Montagu] to the E of M, to introduce the son of Sir Francis Child. (Endorsed "Baron Mountague") London, 1707 Jul 31 (Box 10, Folder 53)
  - J. Chetwynd to the E of M, complaining that "things did not go as they ought to do" before Toulon. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 465) Camp at La Vallette, 1707 Aug 3 (Box 10, Folder 54)
  - J. Chetwynd to the E of M, giving an account of the sortie of the French from Toulon, and of subsequent military movements, and concluding with the news that "the Allies were to steal away as they could." (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 470. The beginning is in the form of a journal said, in Cole's Memoirs, to have been sent to Mr. Cole.) Camp at La Vallette, 1707 Aug 3/14 (Box 10, Folder 55)
  - The Duke of Marlborough to the E of M, mentioning that (according to a letter from Mr. Robinson) a conference had been held, at the desire of Count Wratislaw, between Count Piper and the Dutch minister. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 465) Camp at Meldert, 1707 Aug 4 (Box 10, Folder 56)
  - The E of M to Lord Godolphin, requesting the presentation of a letter to the Queen "in relation to passing a Privy Seal for the Plate" the Earl had had of the Crown, as he had now served on three embassies with it. (Draft) Venice, 1707 aUG 5 (Box 10, Folder 57)
  - J. D'Alais to the E of M, announcing that the Elector of Hanover would have his preparations for the expedition to the Rhine completed at the end of the month. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 367) Hanover, 1707 Aug 5 (Box 10, Folder 58)
  - The Earl of Sunderland to the E of M, instructing the latter to ascertain whether the Venetians would be willing to join the Allies and furnish troops if the Imperial garrison were withdrawn from Mantua. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 469) Whitehall, 1707 Aug 5 (Box 10, Folder 59)
  - A. Stanyan to the E of M, mentioning enclosure of a memorial on the subject of the conflicting claims to Neufchâtel, and some information received concerning the position at Toulon. (Printed, in part, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 468) Neufchâtel., 1707 Aug 9 (Box 10, Folder 60)
  - Lord Cowper to the E of M, speculating on the probable issue of the attack on Toulon, about which public feeling was uneasy. Should it succeed, he says, "I apprehend through the transport of joy, or the effect of it here, where good fellowship is in fashion, we should be in danger of losing no small number of honest men in the cause at home." Herlingfordbury, 1707 Aug 10 (Box 10, Folder 61)
  - Sir John Norris to the E of M, announcing the retreat of the Allied army and the departure of the fleet from before Toulon. He had always "had a doubt if a certain man was earnestly desirous of this expedition." He would, if he had the opportunity, give the Earl verbally his "real opinion on that matter, and the present misfortune." On board the Torbay before Toulon, 1707 Aug 11 (Box 10, Folder 62)
  - J. Addison to the E of M, touching very briefly on various topics. (Printed, almost in full, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 472) Whitehall, 1707 Aug 12 (Box 10, Folder 63)
  - Sir P. Medows to the E of M, to the effect that orders had been sent to Count Martinitz to permit the Duke of Savoy to draw out "what number [of troops] he judged reasonable." M. Mellarede had been at Vienna since the Earl left, and was not less dissatisfied. The Austrians were making merry at the past attempts to dissuade them from the Naples expedition, which alone had been successful. The fate of Europe was like to turn on the good behaviour, conduct, and success of his Royal Highness. Vienna, 1707 Aug 13 (Box 10, Folder 64)
  - Lord Godolphin to the E of M, instructing him to take the first opportunity of proposing to the Republic of Venice to enter into the Grand Alliance, and support the Allies with 10,000 or 12,000 men, and mentioning the terms which were to be offered: viz., the troops to be commanded by a General of their own, a subsidy to be allowed, and peace not to be made without notice to the Venetians, and their participation in it. Windsor, 1707 Aug 15 (Box 10, Folder 65)
  - E. Lewis to the E of M. Lord Peterborough had been ordered to "prepare a relation in writing of what he had done abroad in execution of his commission." Mr. Scott, one of the Chamberlains at Hanover, had been "intriguing to promote the invitation," but had been disavowed by the Elector. It was expected that the Duke of Devonshire would "have his Father's staff [as Lord High Steward], and that the E of M would have his Guards again. (Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii., 244) Whitehall, 1707 Aug 26 (Box 10, Folder 66)
  - J. Addison to the E of M, touching very briefly on various topics. It was hoped that the Duke of Marlborough would "set all things right again, as he had done formerly when affairs were in a more desperate posture." (Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii., 245) Whitehall, 1707 Aug 29 (Box 10, Folder 67)
  - J. Addison to the E of M, mentioning advices from Lisbon to the effect that the French had not followed up their victory at Almanza, and had allowed their adversaries time to recover. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 475) Whitehall, 1707 Aug 18/29 (Box 10, Folder 68)
  - The Duke of Somerset to the E of M. The Duke of Devonshire was dead. Lady E. Savage, old as she was, had married young St. John Manwaring. The Queen was going to Newmarket about the end of September, and the Prince was better and might be able to go there also. Syon, 1707 Aug 19 (Box 10, Folder 69)
  - A. Stanyan to the E of M, describing the growing warmth of the dispute between the Prince de Conti and the Prussian Ambassador for precedence. (The principal part is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 469) Neufchâtel, 1707 Aug 19 (Box 10, Folder 70)
  - Sir. P. Meadows [Medows] to the E of M, giving some particulars of "Count Wratislaw's affair," expressing apprehensions of the progress of the French arms, and mentioning a remittance of 200,000 dollars from France for the service of the Hungarians. (Printed, in part, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 472) Vienna, 1707 Aug 20 (Box 10, Folder 71)
  - Sir Cloudesley Shovell to the E of M, announcing that the siege of Toulon had been raised, and that the allied army had decamped. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 471) Association, before Toulon, 1707 Aug 9/20 (Box 10, Folder 72)
  - A. Stanyan to the E of M to the effect that the hearing of the claims to Neufchâtel had been deferred by the Tribunal at the instance of the Prince de Conti. (The principal part is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 474) Neufchâtel, 1707 Aug 26 (Box 10, Folder 73)
  - Sir P. Medows to the E of M, expressing fears that the King of Sweden intended mischief to the Allies. (Printed, in part, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 474) Vienna, 1707 Aug 27 (Box 10, Folder 74)
  - Henry Newton to the E of M, complaining of the oppression of the Italians by the Germans, and giving news from Naples to Sep. 6, from Toulon to Aug. 25, and from Genoa to Sep. 10. Florence, 1707 Sep 14 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Lord Raby to the E of M, announcing that the King of Sweden had come to an agreement with the Emperor. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 476) Berlin, 1707 Sep 6 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - A. Stanyan to the E of M, giving an account of the preliminary proceedings of the Tribunal for deciding upon the claims to Neufchâtel. (Printed, almost in full, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 476) Neufchâtel, 1707 Sep 6 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - J. Vanbrugh to the E of M on the plans for re-building at Kimbolton, etc. (Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii., 250) London, 1707 Sep 9 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Sir P. Medows to the E of M, announcing that the Treaty with the king of Sweden had been despatched, etc. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 447) Vienna, 1707 Sep 10 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - J. Chetwynd to the E of M, mentioning enclosure of a journal containing an account of the retreat from Toulon. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 447) Salusse, 1707 Sep 11 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - A. Stanyan to the E of M, on the proceedings of the Tribunal for for trying the claims to Neufchâtel. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 478) Neufchâtel, 1707 Sep 13 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - A. Stanyan to the E of M, chiefly on the same subject. (Printed, almost in full, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 480) Neufchâtel, 1707 Sep 16 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - J. Addison to some person addressed as "Sir," announcing the death of Mr. Stepney. (Printed, as having been addressed to Mr. Cole, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 481), 1707 Sep 6 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - The E of M to the Lord Treasurer (Lord Godolphin), on the improbability that the Venetian Republic would be induced to join the Grand Alliance after the failure of the attack on Toulon. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 479) Venice, 1707 Sep 16 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - J. Chetwynd to the E of M, attributing the mishap at Toulon to the indolence and ill-will of some of the Generals of the Allies, and announcing that an attempt was to be made upon Susa and La Perouse. (Printed, almost in full, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 479) Camp at Scalin, 1707 Sep 5/16 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Sir P. Medows to the E of M. It was said that King Charles [III, of Spain] was about to be married. The Venetians were "willing to withdraw their offer," which the Austrian Court had "never embraced." The Savoy Ministers," too, had been alarmed at it, and it was feared that His Royal Highness was soured by the delay in granting him the investitures desired by him. Vienna, 1707 Sep 17 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - The Earl of Sunderland to the E of M, instructing him to continue his efforts to bring the Venetians into the Grand Alliance. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 483) Whitehall, 1707 Sep 23 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - A. Cardonnel [Secretary to the Duke of Marlborough] to Mr. Cole, complaining of the conduct of the Germans, and adding "God preserve us hereafter from such allies." (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 482) Camp at Helchin, 1707 Oct 2 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - J. Addison to the E of M, to the effect that great damage had been done to Toulon by the bombardment before the fleet withdrew, and the French had sunk twenty of their own ships to save them from burning. Lord Peterborough had been ordered to give in his accounts by the following Sunday, and be examined by the Committee of Lords. Whitehall, 1707 Sep 23/Oct 3 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - J. Addison to Mr. Cole, mentioning enclosure of a letter from the Bishop of Salisbury to Erizzo (which the Bishop wished Mr. Cole to superscribe), and giving some particulars of Mr. Stepney's will., 1707 Sep 26 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - A. Stanyan to the E of M, to the effect that the King of Prussia would probably be declared Prince of Neufchâtel, after the withdrawal, under protest, of the other Pretenders. (Printed, almost in full, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 483) Neufchâtel, 1707 Oct 4 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Journal (endorsed J. Chetwynd, esq.) of events including the fall of Susa, etc. (A portion is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 484) Turin, 1707 Oct 5 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - J. Addison to [the E of M?], describing a debate in the House of Commons on the question of continuing the Privy Council in Scotland. "The Scotch members were divided, and spoke very largely and they say well on each side, the rest of the House remaining silent for two hours and giving an obliging attention to their new brethren.", 1707 Dec 6/17 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Signor Cornaro to the E of M, expressing hopes that the Earl would enjoy his sojourn at Venice, especially during the carnival, mentioning an opera sent by the Earl from Vienna, and recommending the music of Mendicanti and Biffi. (In French) Newmarket, 1707 Oct 7 (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - M. Boury to the E of M, informing him that the Duke [of Marlborough] was passing a few hours at the Hague before rejoining the army. He would afterwards proceed to Frankfurt to concert measures with the Electors of Hanover and Mayence. (In French) The Hague, 1707 Oct 7 (Box 11, Folder 21)